<?xml version="1.0"?> 
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [ 
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE"> 
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" > 
%PersProse; 
]>
<TEI.2>
<teiHeader type="text" status="new">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title type="work" n="Inst.">Institutio Oratoria, books 7-9: index</title>
<title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
<author n="Quint.">Quintilian</author>
 <editor role="editor" n="Butler">Harold Edgeworth Butler</editor>
&responsibility;
&fund.AnnCPB;
</titleStmt>
<extent>About 100Kb</extent>
&Perseus.publish;
<sourceDesc>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<author>Quintilian</author>
<title>With An English Translation</title>
 <editor role="editor" n="Butler">Harold Edgeworth Butler</editor>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
<publisher>Cambridge, Mass., Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann, Ltd.</publisher>
<date>1922</date>
</imprint>
</monogr>
</biblStruct>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
<state unit="entry"/>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="en">English</language>
<language id="la">Latin</language>
<language id="greek">Greek</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change><date>2006</date>
<respStmt><name>GRC</name><resp>tagging</resp></respStmt>
<item></item>
</change>

</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text>

<body><div1 type="chapter"><head>Index</head>

<p>(<hi rend="italics">Only those names</hi> are<hi rend="italics">included which seem to require some explanation; a
complete index will be contained in Vol. IV.</hi>)</p>

<p>Aeacida, VII. ix. 6. Pyrrhus, King of Epirus, who claimed descent from Aeacus.</p>
<p>Aeschines, VII. i, 2. Athenian orator, famous as opponent of Demosthenes.</p>
<p>Africanus, Julius, VIII. v. 16. Orator of the reign of Nero.</p>
<p>Antomus, M. (i), VIII. iii. 16. Great orator, earlier contemporary of Cicero.</p>
<p>Antonius, M. (ii), VII. iii. 18. The triumvir.</p>
<p>Antonius, Gaius, IX. iii. 94. Cicero's colleague in the consulship.</p>
<p>Apollodorus, IX. i. 12. Distinguished rhetorician from Pergamus of the Augustan age.</p>
<p>Appius Pulcher, VIII. iii. 35. Cicero's predecessor as governor of Cilicia: the whole of Bk. III of the <hi rend="italics">Epistolae ad Familiares</hi> is addressed to
him.</p>
<p>Asinius, see Pollio.</p>

<p>Bostar, VIII. ii. 10. A man of Punic origin alleged to have been murdered by Scaurus in Sardinia.</p>
<p>Brutus, M., IX. iii. 95; IX. iv. 75. sq. Orator of the Attic school: murderer of Julius Caesar.</p>

<p>Caecilius, VIII. iii. 35; IX. i. 12; IX. iii. 38, 46, 89, 91, 98. Sicilian rhetorician who taught at Rome in the reign of Augustus.</p>
<p>Caecilius, Q. . VII. ii. 2. Sought to accuse Verres, whose quaestor he had been, with a view to securing his acquittal by collusion.</p>
<p>Caelius, IX. ii. 59. Younger contemporary of Cicero, distinguished as an orator.</p>
<p>Calvus, IX. ii. 26; IX. iii. 56. Younger contemporary of Cicero, poet and orator of the Attic school.</p>
<p>Cassius Severus, VIII. ii. 2: VIII. iii. 89. Orator of the reign of Augustus.</p>
<p>Cato the censor, VIII. iii. 29; VIII. v. 33; VIII. vi. 9; IX. ii. 21; IX. iv. 39. The famous opponent of Carthaeo; one of the most distinguished writers and orators of his day (234&ndash;149 B.C.).</p>
<p>Cato Uticensis, VIII. ii. 9; IX. iv. 75. Contemporary of Cicero and among
the most ardent opponents of Caesar.</p>
<p>Celsus, Cornelius, VII. i. 10; VII. ii. 19; VIII. iii. 35, 47; IX. i. 18; IX.
ii. 22, 40, 102, 104. 101; IX. iv. 137. Encyclopedic writer of the reign of Tiberius. His works on rhetoric are lost; a treatise on medicine survives.</p>
<p>Cornelius, VIII. iii. 3. Defended by Cicero on a charge of <hi rend="italics">Iese-majeste.</hi></p>
<p>Cornifieius IX. ii. 27; IX. iii. 71, 89, 98. Rhetorician, contemporary of Cicero, probably author of rhetorical treatise <hi rend="italics">ad Herennium.</hi></p>
<p>Crassus, L., VII. vi. 9; VIII. Pr. 14. Great orator: earlier contemporary
of Cicero.</p>
<p>Ctesiphon, VII. i. 2. Accused by Aeschines and defended by Demosthenes (<hi rend="italics">de Corona</hi>).</p>
<p>Curius. VIII. ii. 38. Famous general, victorious over Pyrrhus: surnamed Dentatus.</p>

<pb id="p.594"/>

<p>Dionysius of Halicarnassus, IX. iii. 89; IX. iv. 88. Famous rhetorician and historian of the Augustan age.</p>
<p>Dolabella, VII. ii. 4. Son-in-law of Cicero.</p>
<p>Domitius Afer, VIII. v. 4 and 16; IX. ii. 20; IX. iii. 66, 79; IX. iv. 31. Famous orator of the reign of Tiberius.</p>

<p>Ephorus, IX. iv. 87. Famous Greek historian (fourth century B.C.): wrote a history of Greece from the earliest times to 341 B.C.</p>

<p>Fabricius, V.ii.38. Famous general, victorious over Samnites and Lucanians, 282 B.C.</p>
<p>Fannius, VII. ix. 12. Consul 122 B.C.</p>
<p>Flavus, see Verginius.</p>

<p>Gallio, IX. ii. 91. Orator and friend of Ovid.</p>
<p>Gorgias (i), IX. iii. 74. Sophist and rhetorician of Leontini, latter half of fifth century B.C.</p>
<p>Gorgias (ii), IX. ii. 102, 106. Athenian rhetorician, teacher of Cicero's son.</p>

<p>Hermagoras, VII. iv. 4; IX. i. 106. Famous rhetorician of the Rhodian school, contemporary with Cicero.</p>
<p>Hirtius, VIII. iii. 54. Supporter of Caesar. Consul 43 B.C. Killed at Mutina while fighting Mark Antony.</p>
<p>Horatius, VII. iv. 8. Survivor of the three Horatii who fought the three Curiatli: slew his sister for bewailing the death of one of the Curiatii to whom she was betrothed.</p>
<p>Hortensius VIII. iii. 35. Cicero's chief rival at the bar.</p>

<p>Isocrates, IX. iii. 74; IX. iv. 35. Famous Athenian orator, founder of the science and technique of Greek rhetoric (436&ndash;338 B.C.).</p>

<p>Labienus, IX. iii. 13. Orator and historian under Augustus.</p>

<p>Mancinus, VII. iv. 12. Consul 137 B.C. Defeated by the armies of the town of Numantia, with whom he concluded a shameful peace, which Rome refused to acknowledge.</p>
<p>Manlius, VII. ii. 2. Saved Rome from the Gauls, but later, suspected of aiming at supreme power, was hurled from the Tarpeian rock, 384 B.C.</p>
<p>Marrucini, VIII. ii. 26. A people on the Adriatic slopes of the Abruzzi.</p>
<p>Messala. VI. iii. 34; IX. iv. 38. Distinguished orator and philologist of
the Augustan age.</p>
<p>Mithridates, VIII. iii. 82. King of Pontus, finally conquered by Pompey.</p>

<p>Pisaurum, VII. ii. 26. The modern Pesaro.</p>
<p>Piso, IX. ii, 61. Praetor in Spain, 113 B.C.</p>
<p>Pollio, Asinius, VII. ii. 26; VIII. i. 3; IX. ii. 9 and 34; IX. iii. 13; IX. iv. 132. Famous orator, poet and historian of the Augustan age.</p>
<p>Pomponius Secundus, VIII. iii. 31. A writer of tragedy under the Empire.</p>
<p>Proculeius, IX. iii. 68. Friend of Augustus.</p>
<p>Proculus, C. Artorius, IX. i 2. A. grammarian of unknown date.</p>
<p>Prodicus, IX. ii. 16. Sophist of the <hi rend="italics">fifth</hi> century B.C.</p>
<p>Pyrrhus, VIII. ii. 6. King of Epirus; invaded Italy in the opening years of the third century B.C.</p>

<p>Rabirius, VII. i. 9 and 16. Killed Saturninus, and was indicted for the murder many years afterwards by Caesar.</p>
<p>Roscius, VIII. ii. 2. Accused of parricide and defended by Cicero.</p>
<p>Rullus, VIII. iv. 28. As tribune, proposed an agrarian law in 63 B.C.</p>
<p>Rutilius, IX. ii. 102 and 106; IX. iii. 84, 89 <hi rend="italics">sqq.</hi> 99. Rhetorician of the reign of Augustus, translated the works of Gorgias of Athens (<hi rend="italics">q.v.</hi>).</p>

<p>Scaevola, Q. (i), VII. ix. 12. Consul 117 B.C.</p>
<p>Saevola (ii), VII. vi. 9. Famous jurist. Consul 95 B.C.</p>
<p>Scaulus, VII. ii. 10. Praetor 56, Propraetor in Sardinia 55 B.C. Accused

<pb id="p.595"/>

of extortion in his province, he was defended by Cicero and acquitted.</p>
<p>Sisenna, VIII. iii. 35. Historian and man of letters with a passion for rare words: elder contemporary of Cicero.</p>
<p>Sulpicius, Servius, VIII. iii. 18. Distinguished orator, contemporary with Cicero, died on embassy to Mark Antony.</p>

<p>Theo, IX. iii.7. Stoic and rhetorician of the reign of Augustus.</p>
<p>Theodectes, IX. iv. 88. Rhetorician of first half of fourth century B.C.</p>
<p>Theophrastus, VII. i. 2; IX. iv. 88.</p>
<p>Theopompus, IX. iv. 35. Famous Greek historian of the latter half of fourth century B.C.</p>
<p>Thrasybulus, VII, iv. 44. Overthrew the thirty tyrants of Athens 404 B.C.</p>
<p>Thrasymachus, IX. v. 87. i. 8 Rhetorician contemporary with Plato.</p>
<p>Trachalus, VIII. v. 19. A distinguished orator, consul 68 A.D. See X. i. 119.</p>

<p>Vatinius, IX. ii. 26. Turbulent politician of the worst character: opponent of Cicero: accused of bribery by Oalvus, 54 B.C.</p>
<p>Verginius Flavus, VII. iv. 24 and 40; VIII. iii. 33. Famous rhetorician, flourished under Nero.</p>
<p>Vibius Crispus, VIII. v. 15 and 17. Orator contemporary with Quintilian: notorious as an informer.</p>

<p>Zoilus, IX. i. 14. Grammarian and rhetorician: fourth or third century B.C., date uncertain.</p></div1>

</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
